<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doome of heretiques: or, A discovery of subtle foxes, who were tyed tayle to tayle, and crept into the Church to doe mischiefe. As it was delivered in a sermon at Wickham-Market in Suffolke, upon the fast day, being the 26 of May. 1647. / By Zeph: Smyth, minister of Gods Word. Imprimatur, Ia: Cranford, August 22. 1648.</title>
            <author>Smyth, Zeph. (Zephaniah), fl. 1646-1648.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E467_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863874</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E467[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doome of heretiques: or, A discovery of subtle foxes, who were tyed tayle to tayle, and crept into the Church to doe mischiefe. As it was delivered in a sermon at Wickham-Market in Suffolke, upon the fast day, being the 26 of May. 1647. / By Zeph: Smyth, minister of Gods Word. Imprimatur, Ia: Cranford, August 22. 1648.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, Zeph. (Zephaniah), fl. 1646-1648.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Rothwell, at the Sunne and Fountaine in Pauls churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLVIII. [1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber ye 11th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOOME OF HERETIQUES: OR, A diſcovery of ſubtle Foxes, who were tyed tayle to tayle, and crept into the Church to doe miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered in a Sermon at Wickham-Market in Suffolke, upon the Faſt day, being the 26 of <hi>May.</hi> 1647.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Zeph: Smyth,</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Take we the Foxes, the little Foxes, which deſtroy the vines, for our vines have ſmall grapes.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cant. 2.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>For there are certaine men crept in which before were of old ordained to this condemnation, ungodly men they are, which turne the grace of God into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and deny God the only Lord, and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jude ver. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Ia: Cranford, Auguſt</hi> 22. 1648.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Rothwell,</hi> at the Sunne and Fountaine in <hi>Pauls</hi> churchyard. MDCXLVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:162305:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:162305:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IT ſhall not need to ſeeme ſtrange to us if the truth meet with oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; nothing happens in this kind but what the Apoſtle did long ago foretell, That in the laſt days ſhould come perillous times, <hi>2 Tim. 3.1.</hi> The times are perillous when the truth is oppoſed, as verſe the eighth, the Father of errour and lyes, and his Miniſters alſo, transforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Angels of Light, that craftily they might undermine the truth, and exalt errour: Bleſſed is he that now keepeth his garments, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut woe be to them that God out of a juſt judgement gives up to ſtrong deluſions, to beleeve lyes, that they might be damned which beleeve not the truth, <hi>2 Theſ. 2.11.</hi> becauſe they received not the truth in the love of it. It is not unknowne to many what oppoſition this enſuing Sermon met withall; at the preaching of it ſome ſcoffed, and the Sermon being ended, a company which were at the High Constables houſe of the ſaid Towne in the Sermon time came into the Congregation, who with ſome others that heard the Sermon, which belong to them, made a diſturbance in the Congregation, calling the doctrine which was there delivered, a doctrine of devils; the ſaid High Conſtable alſo with divers others in the Towne, as I was credibly informed, did ſcoffe at this doctrine, ſaying, it was not fit to be preached, and threatned it ſhould be contradicted in print; and have ever ſince endeavoured to make the Author odious by inventing falſhoods, ſlanders, and charging him with ſcandals falſly; but to paſſe by this, what was then oppoſed is now made publique; that <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s I have peace of conſcience in that I then delivered, ſo alſo all Orthodox Miniſters and people that ſhall peruſe it, may judge whether it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ary to Scripture, or the judgement of the learned as <hi>Calvin, Urſinus, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucanus, Peter Martyr, Perkins,</hi> with divers others, whoſe labours the Lord hath abundantly bleſſed, and made advantagious to the Church. I calling to mind how duty binds me, and the Oath of God lyes upon me to defend the truth againſt hereſies and ſchiſmes, and that I ought not to be aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt, for it is the power of God to ſalvation, <hi>Rom. 1.16.</hi> have adventured to owne my doctrine in a more publique place then <hi>Wickham-market</hi> Pulpit; beeng fully aſſured, that though men and devils ſhould oppoſe the truth what they can, yet at the length truth ſhall prevaile; in the interim it is good to pray and wait. It much behooves the Saints now, ſo many of them as remaine ſtedfaſt and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the faith, which have not yet attained to this learning, neither
<pb facs="tcp:162305:3"/>have knowne theſe depths of Satan, to hold faſt that which they have already, <hi>Rev. 2.24, 25.</hi> and to mourn for the ſins of the times. Did rivers of water run down <hi>Davids</hi> eyes, becauſe men kept not Gods laws, <hi>Pſ. 119.136.</hi> and ſhall not we grieve to heare men deny the law, and ſay it ought not to be preached? Did <hi>David</hi> grieve becauſe the wicked kept not Gods word, <hi>Pſ. 119.158.</hi> and ſhall not we grieve to heare men deny the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be the word of God; and ſay it repents them they have faſted and prayed and mourned ſo much for their ſins? how little doe theſe men and women conſider, that though a Chriſtian ſhould be out of all duty in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of dependance, yet they ſhould be in al duty in reſpect of performance? Our differences are not meerly about things circumſtantiall but ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall; and the effects are very ſad; they tend to the devouring of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to the making Religion odious to the world; they keep off people from comming in to Ieſus Christ; they either diſcourage weak Chriſtians, or pervert them; they hinder Chriſtian communion, and comfortable ſociety one with another; in ſtead of faſting and praying, and mourning, and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God together, and edifying one another in their moſt holy faith, there are contentions, ſtrifes, janglings, &amp; hatred, and is not this cauſe of mourning? yea is not this one thing that provokes God to be at a controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with us? As if he ſhould ſay to us as he did once to the Iewes, Shall I not viſit for theſe things? In the day of the Lords wrath it is better to be found mourners in Sion then ſinners in Sion; therefore now ſhould be the Saints praying time, and morning-time, even to give the Lord no reſt untill he compoſe our differences, and bring order out of our confuſions, Who alone is able to do it, and without he do it none elſe can, neither King nor Parliament, nor Armies; it is he muſt reconcile his people to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and one to another. The Lord is my witneſse, that I have not put forth this Sermon out of bitterneſſe of ſpirit againſt them that differ from me; or out of deſire of applauſe, having nothing to beaſt of my own, except it be of my nothingneſſe; but to let the world judge of that doctrine which people were ſo much taken off from by the oppoſite party. It is poſsible the lines may be offenſive to many; partly becauſe the matter comes abroad in a plaine dreſſe; and partly becauſe it is ſo contradictory to mens fantaſies; to which I anſwer, if God in his word cannot pleaſe all, I muſt not looke to doe it. I deſire the Reader firſt to read and then judge; if it may tell any a ſtory of heaven, it ſatisfies him who is yours in Chriſt Ieſus,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ze: Smyth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:162305:3"/>
            <head>A Diſcoverie of the Churches Danger, by ſeeming Friends.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jude 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For there are certaine men crept in which before were of old ordained to this Gondemnation, ungodly men they are, which turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, and deny God the onely Lord, and the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iude</hi> in this Epiſtle gives the ſaints warning to take heed of ſeducers. Such were crept into the Church as would delude them unawares, who would not onely deny the truth themſelves, and turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, but they would doe what in them lay to ſeduce others: as it hath alwayes been the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of heretiques, when they have once ingaged themſelves in the ſervice of building up the kingdome of Satan, by denying the truth and hearkening unto Satans lyes and deluſions, to procure as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they can by ſubtilty and cunning craftineſſe deceive, to joyne with them in the worke.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle likewiſe ſheweth the danger of being ſeduced by them; and that is drawn from the Judgements that will moſt certainely light upon them, not onely upon ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but upon the ſeduced; as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.22. God doth not onely threaten to caſt <hi>Iezabel</hi> into a bed of ſorrow &amp; great affliction, but them alſo which commit fornication with her; ſo that thoſe which are ſeduced are in great danger, as well as they which ſeduce; and the certainty of their judgements the Apoſtle proves from three examples of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon others, <hi>viz.</hi> the judgment which he brought upon the murmuring Iſraelites, who though God brought them out of the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet deſtroyed them in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe: Secondly, of the Angels who were not ſpared, but throwne downe from heaven, and are reſerved in everlaſting chains under darknes unto the judgement of the great day: Thirdly, the burning of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> with fire and brimſtone from heaven, and the Cities about them. And what? did God ſo ſeverely plague them, and will he let theſe eſcape? No verily, as if the Apoſtle ſhould have ſaid, as he hath plagued them, ſo he will not let theſe ſeducers goe ſcorfree; and this he proves, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth from <hi>Adam,</hi> prophecied concerning ſuch, Behold, the Lord cometh with thouſands of his ſaints to give judgement againſt all men; and to rebuke the ungodly: and the Apoſtle ſpeakes of the ſame ungodly perſons, that the text ſpeaks of; and therefore there will be no eſcaping of Gods judgements. If God come armed againſt a people, who
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:162305:4"/>ſhall be able to ſtand againſt God? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14. Can thy heart indure, or can thy hands be ſtrong in the day that I pleade with thee? as if the Lord ſhould have ſaid, thou canſt not indure it, but thy heart will faile, and thy hands will be weake; ſo though ſeducers be audacious before men, yet when God calls them to account, then they ſhall not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand.</p>
            <p>In the begining of the Epiſtle, foure things are conſiderable: Firſt, the perſon wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; Secondly, the perſons to whom he writ; Thirdly, the ſalutation; and Fourthly, that he intended in writing. From the perſon writing three things are conſiderable, <hi>viz.</hi> his name, his office, and his kindred; his name, <hi>Iude;</hi> his office, he was an Apoſtle, one of the twelve Apoſtles which our Saviour Chriſt choſe to preach the Goſpell; thirdly, his kindred, he was the brother of <hi>Iames;</hi> of which <hi>Iudas Iames</hi> brother we read was one of the twelve Apoſtles, who is called by the Evangeliſt Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> in <hi>Chap.</hi> 10 3. <hi>Lebbeus Thaddeus,</hi> and the ſame man which is here called <hi>Lebbeus Thaddeus,</hi> is called in <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Iudas Iames</hi> brother, and to diſtinguiſh him from <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traitor, they are named as two diſtinct perſons in the ſame <hi>verſe,</hi> which will be very cleare if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.22. with <hi>Acts</hi> 1.31.</p>
            <p>It is the judgement of reverend Divines, that this Apoſtle Saint <hi>Jude</hi> out-lived many of the other Apoſtles, even in the dayes of <hi>Domitian</hi> the Emperour; at which time all ſorts of people grew deſperately wicked, corruption did abound both in doctrine and manners, inſomuch as many to whom the Apoſtles had preached Chriſt, laying open the doctrine of free grace, they waxed wanton and made it a doctrine of liberty, turning the grace of God into wantonneſſe; and this Apoſtle perceiving it very well, he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zealous in admoniſhing the Saints to take heed of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the perſons to whom he writ, and that is not to a particular perſon, or Church, as <hi>Paul</hi> when he writ to <hi>Philemon,</hi> or as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> when he writ to the elect Lady and to the beloved <hi>Gaius,</hi> but this is writ to all the Saints in generall, all them ſanctifyed and called in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> the whole Church was in danger by reaſon of ſeducers, and therefore the Apoſtle writes an Epiſtle of very great concernment unto the whole Church.</p>
            <p>The Third thing conſiderable is his ſalutation, in which the Apoſtle wiſhes the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of three things, <hi>viz.</hi> mercy, peace and love.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing conſiderable is that the Apoſtle did intend in writing this Epiſtle; which was to confirme the Sainis in the truth, and to keep them to their principles they had learned, in ſuch times as many did change their true principles for falſe, and turned from the truth to fables; therefore in the 3 <hi>ver.</hi> When, ſaith the Apoſtle, I gave all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to write to you about the common ſalvation, it was needfull for me to write unto you that you ſhould earneſtly contend for the maintenance of the faith which was once given unto the Saints; here we muſt obſerve that ſalvation is called common in three reſpects.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it is generally offered both to the elect and reprobate; thoſe were invited to the ſupper of the King of Heaven <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. who were rejected and never taſted of it; none of thoſe that were bidden ſhall taſte of my Super; and many are called, but few are choſen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. and of foure ſorts of hearers which are ſpoken of <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. who are compared to the foure ſorts of ground, three ſorts get no good.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it is the way that all thoſe walke in that are ſaved; there is but one way truth and life, which is Chriſt Jeſus; neither is there any other name under heaven whereby a man can be ſaved. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12. There is not one way for the Jewes and another way for the Gentiles, one way for the ſervant, and another way for the ſonne; but it is the common way that all have gone that ever have beene ſaved from the beginning of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162305:4"/>the world unto this day, they have been ſaved by Jeſus Chriſt who is the Author of eternal ſalvation, to all that obey him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to confute the new fantaſtique wayes which many goe about to finde out to heaven; ſome have not been aſhamed to ſay they have found out a broader way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then ever Jeſus Chriſt knew of; for whereas Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.14. Straite is the way that leadeth to life, who knew the way very well, and whither many or few ſhould walke in it, he being the way himſelfe, yet they ſay all ſhall be ſaved; and to ſay ſome ſhall be damned they call it a doctrine of Devills, not fit to be taught; I might inſtance many more who ſuppoſe they have found a very good way to heaven, as the Civillian, the meere morall man, the preſumptuous, with others, which notwithſtanding they have a good opinion of their wayes; yet their way is the broad road to hell; this is called the common onely way, to ſhew the vanity of all other wayes.</p>
            <p>Next, that ye would contend for the faith once given to the Saints; in that the Apoſtle exhorts the Saints to contend for the faith; I underſtand by faith he meaneth the true ſincere doctrine of Chriſt which the Apoſtles had taught the Saints, and which they did beleeve; ſometimes in Scripture faith is put for doctrine, as 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.1. Many ſhall depart from the faith, that is, the doctrine of the faith; for many in Saint <hi>Judes</hi> time forſook thoſe wholſome truths that the Apoſtles had taught them, and turned to fables, and made the doctrine of Chriſt a doctrine of liberty, of which ſort of perſons the Apoſtle deſcribes at large in this Epiſtle: and this is the duty the Apoſtle exhorts the ſaints to in the text, to contend for the truth, and ſtand up in the defence of it in ſuch evill and backſliding dayes as thoſe were.</p>
            <p>And the ground and reaſon why the ſaints ſhould contend for the maintenance of the faith once given to the Saints, is layd downe in my Text, For there are certain men crept in unawares which before were ordained to this condemnation; by this time you may perceive who the Apoſtles meanes in the Text, Heretiques, and they are deſcribed by theſe five things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, by their number, There are certain men crept in, not one or two, but many, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.5. Many will come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many, and therefore the danger is the greater.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By their place, They are in the Church; therfore ſaith the Apoſtle, They are crept in amongſt the ſaints; and in this regard the danger is the greater; if the enemies have once invaded a land, that land is in the more danger, it concernes the inhabitants to looke about them; if the fire be kindled in the thatch of the houſe, it concernes all within the houſe to make haſte to quench it: ſo when ſeducers are in the Church it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne all the ſaints to contend for the truth, and to keep their garments.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are deſcribed by their ſubtilty, They are crept in, they do not come in the honeſt plain ſimple way, but by craftes and ſubtilties, and therfore there is the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. If you have them that are crafty and ſubtill about you, you will where ever you ſee them looke to your ſelves; truly it were good the ſaints would be as carefull for their ſoules, there are crafty ſubtill people abroad, therefore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.14. be no more children wavering and carried about with every winde of doctrine by the deceit of men and with craftineſſe whereby they lye in wait to deceive; it were good the ſaints where ever they ſee them would look to Gods word and take heed of them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, They are deſcribed by their condition, They were of old ordained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, By their practiſes, They are ungodly, Secondly, They turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe. Thirdly, They deny God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>From the deſcription of the perſons by their number, Certaine, and their place, In the
<pb facs="tcp:162305:5"/>Church, they are crept in amongſt the Saints and are accounted ſaints, I may ſafely ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this point of doctrine,</p>
            <p>That all are not true Saints that externally ſeeme to be ſaints: my method in handling of the doctrine ſhall, God aſſiſting, be Firſt to prove it; Secondly, to make application.</p>
            <p>For the confirmation of the point I ſhall endeavour to make it appear to be a truth that all are not ſaints that externally ſeeme to be ſuch both amongſt teachers and hearers; firſt amongſt teachers, all thoſe teachers that externally ſeeme to be holy and ſincere, are not ſo, the proof ſee in <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.70. Have not I ſaith Chriſt choſen twelve of you, and one of you is a devill, now he ſpake this of <hi>Judas</hi> ſaith the Text; yet <hi>Iudas</hi> it is like was very exact to outward appearance, he could pray and preach, worke miracles, caſt out devills; inſomuch, as when our Saviour Chriſt ſaid one of you ſhall betray mee, they did all ſuſpect themſelves rather then <hi>Iudas,</hi> one ſais is it I? and another, is it I? implying that <hi>Iudas</hi> did walke ſo exactly that he was not ſuſpected; and further ſee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. Beware ſaith Chriſt of falſe prophets, which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but are inwardly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening wolves, they externally ſeeme holy and ſincere, but the inſide is naught; it is not all that come in the name of Chriſt that are the true miniſters of Chriſt; for ſeducers come in the name of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.5. Many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and deceive many; they deceive many, yea, if it were poſſible the very elect, and yet come in the name of Chriſt, yea Satans Miniſters will come in the name of Chriſt and under the notion of holineſſe. 26 <hi>or.</hi> 11.13. ſuch falſe Apoſtles are deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workers and transforme themſelves into the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt: I pray marke, the falſe Apoſtles put on the ſhape of the true ones, and I pray who are theſe falſe Apoſtles? Satans miniſters, as appeares in the next verſe: no marvel for Satan himſelfe is transformed into an angell of light, and therefore no marvell if his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters transforme themſelves; they are ſatans miniſters, and yet looked upon as holy men, ſo you ſhall finde 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. ſuch Chaplains as creep into houſes, and lead ſimple woemen captive: ſuch as were proud, covetous, covenant violaters, and what not, yet they had a forme of godlineſſe; ſo that you may ſee it is very plaine, that all ſuch teachers as ſeeme to be ſaints, are not true ſaints.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as amongſt teachers ſo amongſt heaters, all are not true ſaints that ſeeme to be ſo, They went out from us: but they were not of us ſaith the Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Ioh</hi> 2.19 they ſeemed to be ſaints a great while, but were hypocrites: we read of the ſtony ground <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20 that it had a ſhew of corne, the ſeed ſprung up, but came to nothing; yet the ſtony heaters went far, they did not onely heare the word, but receive it with joy, they were glorious profeſſors, and who would not but have taken ſuch for ſaints, as did heare, read, faſt, pray, make ſuch a glorious profeſſion, ay but a winter of affliction and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution diſcovered them to be hypocrites, when a perſecution came, becauſe of the word, they were offended: all are not true ſaints that externally ſeem ſaints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> Is for admonition to the people of God, take heed of them amongſt your ſelves, al that put on a viſard of Saints are not true ſaints, there are many teachers, many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors ſpeake of God with their tongues, and deny him with their lives, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. they profeſſe they know God but in workes deny him, and are abominable, and to every good worke a reprobate: you know how corrupt thoſe heritiques were, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. and yet they had a forme of godlineſſe; if thoſe amongſt the ſaints be ſuch, the ſaints had need take heed of them: for the Church is in great danger by reaſon of ſuch: Chriſt was betrayed by a <hi>Judas</hi> one of his twelve Apoſtles; the Church is in danger of being undermined by falſe brethren <hi>Gal.</hi> 2 4. we read of falſe brethren who crept into the Church to ſpie out their liberty and to bring them into bondage; there were ſome crept into the Church to undermine the Church, and the Church is never worſe undermined then by ſuch; a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162305:5"/>enemy is dangerous, but a domeſticke is more dangerous; when a mans enemie are in his family, that man is in danger: ſo when the Churches enemies are among themſelves, under the vizard of ſaints, that is, when men under pretence of ſetting up truth, undermine truth; under a pretence of holineſſe, undermine holineſſe; under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of religion, undermine religion; then the Church muſt needs be in great danger, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.29, 30. I know ſaith the Apoſtle, after my departure ſhall grievous wolves enter in amongſt you; yea, men amongſt your ſelves ſhall ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw diſciples after them; I pray marke, amongſt your ſelves; the ſaints had need take heed of thoſe amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> If the Church be in ſuch danger by reaſon of ſuch, Why doth God permit them in the Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For the good of the Church: Firſt, That ſuch as are approved may be knowne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. There muſt be hereſies, that ſuch as are approved may be knowne; when hereticks who are accounted ſaints a long time, goe about to undermine religion, by broaching corrupt doctrine, you ſhall ſoone ſee ſuch as wanted ſound hearts, ſuch as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver received the truth in the love of it, imbrace corrupt doctrine; yea it may be, <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Arminianiſme, Pelagianiſme, Familiſme,</hi> and what not? I tell you theſe are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted precious truths amongſt many hereticks in theſe dayes, and God permits it that ſound hearted Chriſtians might bee diſcovered from thoſe that are not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> God permits ſuch in the Church, that the ſcriptures might be fulfilled; Chriſt is a preclous ſtone to ſome, and a ſtone of ſtumbling unto others, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. It was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſaith the Apoſtle, that ſome ſhould ſtumble at Ieſus Chriſt; and the lying ſignes and wonders, and ſtrange opinions of hereticks on the one ſide, and their hypocriſies cauſe many to ſtumble at Jeſus Chriſt; and thus they fulfill the ſcriptures, to their owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> God permits it, that ſound Chriſtians might looke to their owne hearts; when our Saviour Chriſt ſaid to his diſciples, One of you ſhall betray me, every one was ready to begin at home, Is it I Lord? and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, Is it I? So when the ſaints heare many amongſt themſelves in the Church ſeeme to be godly, and yet are not; many <hi>Judaſes,</hi> many ſtony hearers, many falſe brethren, many that have knowledg and gifts and parts, that are naught, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22. Many will in that day ſay, Lord, Have we not in thy name prophecyed, and in thy name caſt out devils? and yet Jeſus Chriſt will ſay, depart, I never knew you, this will put Chriſtians on to enquiry, Is it I? Oh I pray God it may not be I. And thus God permits it that ſound Chriſtians might look to their hearts, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Vſe.</hi> Is for information. It informes us that a bare profeſſion is not enough to make a man a true Chriſtian; a man may be a glorious profeſſor of religion, and yet be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as well as <hi>Judas;</hi> yet it is very ſtrange to ſee how people doe deceive themſelves with this; what ſayes one? I was baptized, I keep my Church, and pay every man his owne, and we live under the Ordinances, and can cry, the Temple of the Lord, as <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. But let me tell thee, thou mayeſt doe all this, and more too, and yet be damned; thoſe in <hi>Mat.</hi> that prayed, preached, caſt out devills, wrought miracles in the name of Chriſt, went further then thus, and yet Jeſus Chriſt will ſay to them, Depart, I know you not; <hi>Iudas</hi> went further then thus, and yet a damned wretch; therefore take heed ye reſt not in this, I was baptized, and I am a profeſſor, I keep my Church, and pay every man his owne; many a man hath gone further then ſo, and yet been damned; <hi>Abah</hi> was humbled, and <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> gladly; Nay, ſaith our Saviour <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24. Many ſhall ſeeke to enter in, and ſhall not be able; there may be many in hell that it may be have prayed oftener then thou, been more exact in performing of family duties then thou haſt beene,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162305:6"/>that have tooke more paines in the wayes of God then thou haſt done, and yet have been damned, and therefore take heed of reſting in a bare profeſſion of religion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Exhortation. Let us hence be exhorted, To make ſure we be none of thoſe that are in the Church and yet are not of the Church; we heare of ſome that ſeem to be ſaints, and yet are none; of many that have knowledge and parts, and make a glorious profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and yet may be damned; let it be our care to make ſure we be none of them; for their condition is worſe then the condition of others; for upon them ſhall theſe Scriptures be fulfilled; he that increaſeth knowledge, increaſeth ſorrow; how doth he increaſe ſorrow? by not practiſing what he knew; for it had beene better never to have knowne the way of God, then after to turne from the holy Commandement. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But if it be ſo, how ſhall I know I am none of theſe perſons you ſpeake of who ſeem to be ſaints, and yet are not? and by what rule ſhould I judge another man to be a true childe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, Examine the foundation thou haſt built upon; a true beleever builds upon Chriſt the Rocke, and therefore the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt him; there are a great many build upon their duties and profeſſion, and not upon Chriſt; ſome upon their ſweet conceits and fancied comforts in Chriſt, but not upon Chriſt indeed; but canſt thou ſay thou doſt truly beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt? that thou haſt ſuch a faith as was not of thine owne fancying, but wrought by the mighty operation of the Holy Ghoſt? <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. ſuch a faith as purifies the heart? <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. as workes by love? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. as is fruitfull in good workes? <hi>James</hi> 2.26. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8. this is a good ſigne that thou art a true ſaint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> If thy heart be upright, that is another good evidence; if thy care be to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thy heart to God, rather then to the world, thy conſcience can witneſſe as in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God to thee that thou deſireſt that God might ſee thy heart upright rather then man ſhould thinke it is upright, and thou canſt ſay with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 139. Examine my reines and my heart, and ſee if there be any way of wickedneſſe in me; then this is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good ſigne thou art a true ſaint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Doſt thou hold ſuch ſound principles as faints ſhould do? as the Apoſtle exhorts the ſaints in this Epiſtle, To contend for the truth; ſo do you ſtand up in defence of the truth againſt hereticks and hereſies; and do you lead ſuch lives as faints ſhould do, <hi>viz.</hi> to live holily, righteouſly and ſoberly, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. And canſt thou ſay ſo far as thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thine owne heart, thou art at Gods command, to goe when he bids thee go, and come when he bids thee come? theſe are good evidences thou art a true ſaint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> There are ſome notes of tryall, whereby thou mayeſt perſwade thy ſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning another that he or ſhe is a true ſaint.</p>
            <p>Firſt, when thou feeſt they are as carefull to walke cloſe with God in a generall and particular calling, at home as well as abroad; many are zealous abroad amongſt ſuch as will obſerve them, who but they for religion, but if you follow theſe men home, then <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be yee ſhall ſee they neither regard body nor ſoule; are faithfull neither in the duties of their generall calling, nor particular neither; truly if it be ſo, that man or womans heart is very ſuſpicious.</p>
            <p>Secondly. A gracious man is an humble man; That ſoul that God makes his reſidence withall, is an humble ſoule; I dwell with the humble ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 57.15. and I will looke to him that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2. When we ſee a ſoule walke humbly with God, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8. this may give good evidence to others that ſuch a one is godly; and on the contrary, it makes ſuch ſuſpicious as are proud, ſelf-conceited, eſteeme well of themſelves, and are ready to ſcorne others.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:162305:6"/>
            <p> Thirdly. When we ſee men and women eſtabliſhed in the truth, this gives good evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence unto others of their uprightneſſe, as ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2 7. Rooted and built up in him, and eſtabliſhed in the faith: not like the wandring ſtars <hi>Iude</hi> 13. which runne from one errour to another, untill they have loſt all truth, but fixed ſtaires eſtabliſhed in the truth, ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, and abundant in the worke of the Lord. When wee ſee them ſo eſtabliſhed, as nothing can remove them, but with <hi>Paul</hi> are willing to be bound and to dye for the Lord Jeſus; this man gives good evidence of an upright heart: it is the expreſſion of <hi>Salomon, Pro.</hi> 14.15. The foole beleeveth every thing, but the prudent man will conſider his goings.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. A man gives others good teſtimony of his uprightneſſe, when he takes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes well; Give admonition to the wiſe, and he will be wiſer ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.9. When reproofe is to him as Jewels of gold, and he ready to ſay, bleſſed be God for this reproof, as <hi>David</hi> who ſaid to <hi>Abigall,</hi> Bleſſed be thou of the Lord, who met me to keep my hand from ſhedding of blood; and in another place, Let the righteous ſmite me for it is a benefit; it is the property of a godly man to take reproofes well; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when a man hates him that reproves in the gate, <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10. and counts him that reproves, an enemy; and ready to ſay, Why doth he reprove me? Is he not as bad himſelf, and I could have charged him with as much as he charged me, and I know as much by him as he doth by me, theſe expreſſions ſavour of a bad heart.</p>
            <p>Fifthly. A man gives others good evidence of his uprightneſſe, when he is not a reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of perſons, but loves the meaneſt ſaint that beares the Image of God, as well as the richeſt; my meaning is not that a godly man ſhould not give that civill reſpect to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that their place calls for, Honour to whom honour belongs; but that I minde you of is, that where there is true grace, there will be a true love and reſpect to thoſe ſaints that go in gray coats, ay and thred-bare coats too, ſuch as go out to their day la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſuch as live in a poor cottage, as well as thoſe that are arrayed in ſilkes and ſattins, and live in ſtately houſes; there is many a man loves ſo much as they ſee of the faſhion in another; and ſo much as they ſee of their opinions in another; but the godly love whatſoever they ſee of God in another, Hereby, ſaith our Saviour, ſhall all men know ye are my diſciples, if yee love one another, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.35. The ſaints love the Image of Chriſt whereſoever it is.</p>
            <p>So that yee ſee beloved that though all that externally ſeeme to be ſaints, are not; yet there is a poſſibility for a man to know himſelfe to be a true ſaint, and to be perſwaded that another is a true ſaint. Wee come in the next place to that which followeth; and here I might inſiſt upon their coming into the Church, which is ſubtily, They creep in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares; but I intend not to ſpeake of that now, but to come to the point of doctrine, which ariſes from their condition, Which were of old ordained to condemnation; for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the doctrine of Reprobation held forth in the Text, I ſhall inſiſt upon that, and handle it ſomewhat more generall then as it concernes the perſons ſpoken of in the Text; the doctrine therefore is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God did of old ordaine ſome unto condemnation.</hi> And becauſe it is a doctrine not often inſiſted upon, and at this time is denyed, I intend to prove it from Scripture. Secondly, To give you the reaſon. Thirdly, Anſwer objections. Fourthly, Make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. But before I come to the proofe of the doctrine, it is very neceſſary that I ſhould ſhew you what Reprobation is. Predeſtination hath two parts, Election, and Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for it is Gods eternall and unchangeable decree to ſave ſome of the loſt race of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and to paſſe by others, leaving them under ſinne in a ſtate of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, as they were leſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> without any poſſibility of mercy; ſo that Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162305:7"/>is Gods eternall and unchangeable decree to paſſe by ſome of the Ioſt race of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> leaving them in that condition they were loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> without any poſſibility of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering for ever.</p>
            <p>Firſt. It is Gods decree, you have the proofe in the Text, They were of old ordained to Condemnation, ſo 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.8. To which they were ordained, it was ordained that they ſhould ſtumble at Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly. To paſſe by ſome, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 12, 13. For the Children not being yet borne, neither having done any good or evill, that the purpoſe of God according to Election might ſtand, not of workes, but of him that calleth; it was ſaid too here, The elder ſhall ſerve the younger; as it is written, <hi>Iacob</hi> have I loved, <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated; here we ſee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God choſe ſome, and paſſed by others, not for foreſeene works and merits; for God ſaw nothing in <hi>Iacob</hi> that deſerved his love, more then he ſaw in <hi>Eſau;</hi> but he choſe ſome and rejected others, becauſe it ſo pleaſed him; therefore ſaith the Apoſtle That the purpoſe of God might ſtand; ſo that it is plaine, that it was Gods purpoſe to paſſe by ſome of the loſt race of <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly. They are left without any poſſibility of recovering for ever, becauſe Gods decree to leave them under ſinne and condemdation, cannot be altered, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. the counſel of the Lord ſhal ſtand for evermore, his purpoſe is unchangeable, yea it is as impoſſible for the Reprobate to be ſaved, as it is for God to change and alter his purpoſe; ſo that though Chriſts death was ſufficient in it ſelfe, to ranſome not onely a world, but many thouſands of worlds; yet it was never intended by the Father in giving of his ſonne to dye, or by the Sonne in laying downe his life, that the Reprobate ſhould be ſaved, or that Chriſts derth ſhould fruſtrate Gods decree; and therefore ſee how ineffectuall all the Ordinances of God are to the Reprobate; the Lord hath ordained that by the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe of preaching he will ſave them that beleeve; but the Word is a condemning let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Reprobate, the ſavour of death unto death; it makes their hearts far; I pray ſee <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.37, 38, 39. Though he did many miracles before them, yet they beleeved not, that the ſaying of <hi>Iſaias</hi> might be fulfilled, Lord who hath beleeved our report? they did not beleeve, for <hi>Iſaias</hi> ſaith who hath beleeved? there are ſome are come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods decree, and come under ſuch ſcriptures ſo as they cannot beleeve; they could not beleeve, why ſo? they were come under this ſaying of <hi>Iſaias,</hi> ſo that they could not; there are ſome ſhall fulfill theſe Scriptures to their greater deſtruction, and therefore in the 39. <hi>verſe</hi> they could not beleeve, for <hi>Iſaias</hi> ſaith, He hath blinded their eyes and harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth their hearts; I pray marke, they could not becauſe <hi>Iſaias</hi> ſaith; now if you demand how God hardens their hearts, and blindes their mindes, I anſwer, By puniſhing ſinne with ſinne, giving them up to the hardnes of their hearts, and blindnes of their mindes, leaving them to themſelves to go on in the way to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Next, the cauſes of Reprobation are theſe; the efficient moveing cauſe is Gods good will and pleaſure, to leave the ſinner in that miſerable eſtate into which he is fallen in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Mat.</hi> 11.26. Thou doſt hide theſe things from the wiſe, and underſtanding, why? for becauſe it is his good will and pleaſure, ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. He hath mercy on whom he will, and whom he will he hardeneth, and <hi>verſe</hi> 21. hath not the Potter power of the clay to make of the ſame lumpe, one veſſell to honour, and another to diſhonour? are we not all in the hands of God, as the clay is in the hands of the Potter? may the Potter of the ſame piece of clay make one veſſell for honour, and another for diſhonour, and may not the Lord if he pleaſe? therefore ſaith the Apoſtle in <hi>verſe</hi> 22. What if God will ſhew his wrath? ſo that the efficient cauſe is the good pleaſure of his will.</p>
            <p>Secondly. The finall cauſe is the eternall glory of Gods Juſtice, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. He hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162305:7"/>created all things for his glory, and the wicked for the day of wrath; for in inflicting e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall puniſhment upon the Reprobate, he doth to eternity ſhew his ſeverity againſt, and hatred of ſin. And ſo I come in the next place to the proofe of the doctrine.</p>
            <p>That God did of old ordaine ſome to condemnation, it appeares a truth in the text, ſo in <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.12. Of all that thou haſt given me have I loſt none, but the child of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Scripture might be fulfilled; I pray marke, <hi>Iudaſes</hi> deſtruction was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; God had decreed it from eternity: ſo why did thoſe ſtumble at Chriſt? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. it was ordained they ſhould doe ſo; in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. <hi>Tophet</hi> is prepared of old, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of old that ſome ſhould periſh, for in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. he ſhall ſay to them on his left hand, Go ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for you; Gods wrath is a prepared wrath it is prepared for the wicked; now if wrath were prepared of old, then the wicked who are the veſſels of wrath were ordained to it of old, therefore ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> The wicked are kept unto the day of deſtruction, they ſhall be brought forth in the day of wrath, <hi>Job</hi> 21.30. But here ariſeth an Objection.</p>
            <p>If God did ordaine men to condemnation, he is the Author of it; but God did ordaine ſome to condemnation, <hi>ergo</hi> he is the Author of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Although condemnation be of God foreſeene and ordained, yet none are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, becauſe God did foreſee and appoint it, but becauſe the Reprobates themſelves do ſuch actions as procure damnation, and ſo by their wicked actions they bring to paſſe the eternall counſell of God concerning their damnation, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9.13. Oh Iſrael thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelfe, but in me is thy helpe; as if the Lord ſhould have ſaid, art thou deſtroyed? thou mayeſt thanke thy ſelfe for it; thou mayeſt ſay here is the effect of ſin, this miſery, and woe, and damnation, my ſinne brings upon me; God at the firſt made man righteous, but he ſought out many inventions, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.31. I pray obſerve, man ſought out; ſo that it is men uſe ſuch meanes as procure their condemnation, they are cauſes of their owne ruine.</p>
            <p>Ay but you will ſay, God did did decree thoſe actions as well as their deſtruction for thoſe Actions, for the Text ſaith, God did ordaine that the wicked ſhould ſtumble at Chriſt, and he being the author not onely of the puniſhment, but of the ſinne, alſo he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We muſt make a diſtinction betweene ſinne it ſelfe, and the permiſſion thereof; it is one thing to be the author of ſinne, and another thing to permit ſinne; for as God did decree to paſſe by ſome of the loſt race of <hi>Adam,</hi> he did alſo decree to permit them to uſe ſuch meanes as ſhould bring to paſſe his decree; ſo that <hi>Adams</hi> will was not forced by any violence of Gods purpoſe, compelling him to conſent; but he of a voluntary free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, left God and hearkened to the devill; ſo that it is true, God did decree the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of thoſe actions, and they in doing of thoſe actions bring to paſſe Gods decree, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their damnation, and thus their deſtruction is of themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But you will ſay, God could have prevented thoſe actions that procure our dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, if he would.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, God was not bound to prevent it: he was no more bound to keep <hi>Adam</hi> in the eſtate of innocency, then he was bound to create him and ſet him in that eſtate. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, After he had deſtroyed himſelfe, God was not bound to ſave him, no more then he was bound to create him; and therefore it is no leſſe then blaſphemy to ſay, God is the Author of ſin and condemnation, becauſe he permits ſin, and deſtroyes the creature for ſinne, when he is not bound to prevent it, and it ſtands with his Juſtice to puniſh it.</p>
            <p>Againe we muſt take notice that it is one thing to be the author of an action, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162305:8"/>thing to be the Author of the evill of that action; it is true God did decree that ſuch actions ſhould come to paſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that he would permit <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and all other wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed actions, but God is not the Author of the evill of thoſe actions, but the evill of theſe actions is from our ſelves, and the miſery that followes we bring upon our ſelves, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scripture expreſſion, Thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9.13. and man ſuffers for his ſinne, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.39. Thus God did ordaine ſome to condemnation, he did decree like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to permit them to deſtroy themſelves, as did thoſe who ſtumbled at Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pe.</hi> 2.8. though God did ordaine <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> to condemnation, yet through their ſinnes they bring to paſſe Gods purpoſe; <hi>ſain</hi> his envy, murther, cruelty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation, this brought his ruine and deſtruction; and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by his contempt of God, cruelty to his people; obſtinacy and hardneſſe of heart, wrought out his ruine; ſo <hi>Iudas</hi> his covetouſneſſe, treachery, treaſon to his Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, procured his ruine; ſo hereticks by their pride, vaine glory, ſelfe-conceitedneſſe, wickedneſſe, deceiving, and being deceived, they ruine themſelves, and thus they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bring to paſſe Gods purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Reaſon of the doctrine is, That he might magnifie the glory of his juſtice, as well as the glory of his mercy; the glory of his juſtice, in inflicting puniſhments upon the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells of wrath, and the glory of his mercy in ſaving his people; he hath created all things for his owne glory, and the wicked for the day of wrath, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. For as the godly ſhall for ever ſet forth the glory of his mercy, ſo the wicked ſhall for ever ſet forth the glory of his juſtice.</p>
            <p>We come in the next place to anſwer objections. May ſome ſay, If God hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome to condemnation; how ſhall we know who they bee, or how many there be of them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Secret things belong to God, but things revealed to us and our children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. We have nothing to do to pry into Gods ſecrets, as whether ſo many of a hundred, or ſo many of a thouſand ſhall be ſaved, and the reſt damned; or whether this man or that woman be an elect veſſell, or a reprobate, that is onely knowne unto God; the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God ſtandeth ſure and hath his ſeale; the Lord knowes who are his, and the Lord knowes who are not his, but we know not, neither is it neceſſary that we ſhould know; thus much we may know, that God hath elected ſome and rejected others; for this he hath revealed in his word, and that the number he hath elected, is but a remnant in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the reſt of the world, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. There is but a remnant according to the election of grace; but how many in a towne, or a kingdome, no man can determine; it is not for the miniſter to ſay, ſo many in my pariſh are reprobates, for the houſholder to ſay, ſo many in my family, ſuch a ſonne, or ſuch a daughter, or ſuch a ſervant is a reprobate; we know not but God may let the day of his power come upon them, and bring them in to Jeſus Chriſt; it is not for a particular man to determine concerning himſelfe he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, he knowes not but that God may ſhew mercy to him; therefore we have nothing to do to be ſo curious, as to pry into Gods ſecret counſell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> This doctrine of reprobation is not fit to be preached, becauſe it is the next way to make people deſpaire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, It is a part of Gods counſel, and therefore ought to be preached; how can a Miniſter with <hi>Paul Act.</hi> 20. ſay, I have not ceaſed to make known to you the whole coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God, if they do not with <hi>Paul</hi> teach the doctrine of Reprobation?</p>
            <p>Secondly. It is the doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. Many are called, but few are choſen; the doctrine of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9, 10, 11. <hi>Chapters,</hi> in all three chapters how doth the Apoſtle inſiſt upon Election and Reprobation, and Saint <hi>Iude</hi> in the Text, <hi>Peter</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 2.8.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162305:8"/>did Chriſt live now and the Apoſtles, theſe men would tell them too, their doctrine were not fit to be preached.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. When a fundamentall truth comes to be queſtioned, the queſtion is, Whether becauſe ſome ſuck poyſon, where they might ſuck honey, by ſtumbling at religion, whether the truth ſhould not be preached; ſeeing by the ſame rule we may ſay, Chriſt is a ſtone of ſtumbling unto ſome? therefore Chriſt is not to be preached; though the wicked by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the corruption in their hearts, ſuck poyſon from this doctrine, yet the fault is not in the doctrine, but in their wicked hearts; for the doctrine is rather a doctrine they might ſuck honey from, if they would from hence give all diligence to make their calling and clection ſure.</p>
            <p>But to this doctrine the <hi>Pelagians</hi> are adverſaries alſo, for they deny the doctrine of Reprobation, and affirme that Chriſt dyed for all, without exception, alledging that text in 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1. He is a propitiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſinnes of the whole world.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to this, Firſt, I pray obſerve how theſe men confound Election; for if all be reconciled, where is Election? for to elect is to chuſe out ſome from amongſt the reſt, as <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.19. I have choſen you out of the world, that is, from amongſt the reſt of the world; where I gather, ſome were choſen, and ſome refuſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly. I pray obſerve how they corrupt the true ſenſe of the text, for the world is foure-fold in Scripture, there is the elementary world which God created, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1. and which we read of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. Through faith we underſtand that the world was framed by the word of God, ſo that the things that are ſeen were not made of things which did appeare.</p>
            <p>Secondly. There is the reaſonable world, and that is all mankind without exception, <hi>Ro.</hi> 5.12. By one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death went over all men, that is, all the world, in <hi>Adam</hi> all dye.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. There is the Elect world, and this is ſpoken of in the text, He is a propitiation for our fins, and not ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world, that is, the whole world of beleevers, agreeing with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not imputing their ſins unto them; he doth not ſpeak of ſuch a world as can poſſibly periſh any one of them; for if Chriſt have reconciled them, it is impoſſible any thing paſt, preſent, or to come, ſhould ſeparate them from the love of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. latter end of the Chap. but Chriſt doth reconcile this world, he makes attonement for them, he offered himſelfe a ſacrifice for them, he is a propitiation, not onely for their ſinnes they did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit before converſion, but if after converſion they ſinne through frailty and weakneſſe, he is a propitiation for that too, and none of their fins ſhall be laid to their charge; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayes the text, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. Reconciling the world to himſelfe, not imputing their ſins to them; and if he do not impute their ſinnes to them, they ſhall all be ſaved; but the <hi>Pelagians</hi> themſelves do not affirme that all mankind ſhall be ſaved, but acknowledg ſome of this world may periſh; then let every godly man take notice how they abuſe this text of Scripture, to prove that Chriſt dyed for all the world without exception; when both theſe texts ſpeake of ſuch a world as it is impoſſible any of it ſhould periſh, that is, the world of the Elect; this world of beleevers we read of, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.17. Chriſt came into the world not to condemne the world, but that the world through him might be ſaved, that is, the world of beleevers, as <hi>verſe</hi> 16. That whoſoever beleeve in him ſhould not periſh.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. There is the Reprobate world, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.9. I pray for theſe, I pray not for the world; my kingdom is not of this world; and I have choſen you out of this world, <hi>Jo.</hi> 15.19. and 1 <hi>Io.</hi> 5.19. We know ſaith the Apoſtle we are of God, &amp; the whole world lyes in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe; any underſtanding man may ſee that this world ſpoken of in theſe texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162305:9"/>is not meant that world which the other texts of ſcripture before alledged made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of; but that the other is the world of beleevers, and theſe of the reprobate world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. Who will that all men ſhould be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To expound a text of Scripture in oppoſition to another, is the originall of many abſurdities; of what dangerous conſequence would it be to delude poor ſoules, and tell them Chriſt died for all; for God would that all men ſhould be ſaved, and Chriſt gave himſelfe a ranſome for all? in oppoſition to <hi>Rom.</hi> 9 18. Whom he will he hardeneth, and <hi>verſe</hi> 22. What if God will ſhew his wrath? and in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.39. They could not beleeve, for <hi>Eſaias</hi> ſaith, He hath blinded their eyes and hardened their hearts, and <hi>Mat</hi> 20.16. Many are called but few choſen, ſo that if we compare this with <hi>Rom</hi> 9.18. He hath mercy on whom he will, it is plaine he will all men ſhould be ſaved, that is of all ſorts; not onely Jewes, but Gentiles; not onely rich but poore; he will all ſhould be ſaved, that is, all the Elect, for, As I live, ſaith the Lord, I delight not in the death of a ſinner, as in <hi>Eze.</hi> 18.23 32. But he will not all to be ſaved in reſpect of the force and efficacy of calling and juſtifying them; this the Elect obtaine, and the reſt are hardened. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. And God is not bound to give grace unto them, and inable them to beleeve, he may ſay I made you able at the firſt to do what I required of you and he may juſtly deſtroy the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if it doe not that which he made it able to do at the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the promiſe of grare is univerſall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> To ſay that the promiſe of grace is univerſal, is falſe, yea contrary to Scripture, <hi>Ge.</hi> 3.15. I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed and her ſeed, ſpeaking of the ſeed of the ſerpent the wicked, and the ſeed of the woman the godly, there is a promiſe of Chriſt to the godly, but not to the wicked; ſo ſee <hi>Gal</hi> 3.22. the Scripture hath concluded all under ſinne, that the promiſe of Jeſus Chriſt might be given to them that beleeve; if only to them that beleeve, then the promiſe of grace is not univerſal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. Ro.</hi> 11.32. God hath ſhut up all in unbelief, that he might have mercy upon all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is both Jewes and Gentiles, the Scripture hath concluded all under ſin, that he might have mercy upon all; that is not only upon the Jewes, but upon the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, but his meaning is not that all ſhall be ſaved, for then he muſt contradict himſelfe, in <hi>verſe</hi> the 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. and in <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22. But will have mercy upon all, that is, all the Elect, for we muſt not ſet this Scripture in oppoſition to others; the word All in Scripture doth not alwayes meane the whole world, all mankind without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; for to take the word all ſo generall in Scripture, we may from other texts of Scripture prove that all ſhall be damned, as eaſily as any can prove from this, that all ſhal be ſaved, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. The wicked ſhall turne into hell, and all nations that forget God, take the word all generally, and we may conclude all ſhall be damned, for all have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten God, and the text ſayes, The wicked ſhall turne into hell, and all nations that forget God; ſo <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16 He that beleeveth ſhall not be damned; but this text <hi>Rom.</hi> 11 32. ſhewes that all are ſhut up in unbelief, therefore according to that text in <hi>Mark</hi> all ſhall be damned; ſo whereas he ſayes, That he might have mercy upon all, in <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.26. he ſayes, That he will rejoyce at the deſtruction of the wicked, not that God rejoyces at their ruine as it is a torment and vexation to his creature, but as it is an execution of his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; can God ſave all and yet rejoyce at the deſtruction of the wicked, therefore of neceſſity we muſt underſtand it, that he might have mercy upon all, that is upon all the Elect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> He that taketh a ſufficient ranſome for all, and yet doth not ſave all, is unjuſt; but God taketh a ſufficient ranſome for all, and get doth not ſave all. <hi>Ergo</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:162305:9"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſufficiency of the ranſome doth not bind God to apply it to all; Shew me either where God is bound to it, or hath ingaged himſelfe in ſuch a bond; Suppoſe a thouſand men were ſold for bondſlaves, and ten thouſand pounds de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for their ranſome out of Captivity, and ſuppoſe one man ſhould goe, and ranſome five of that thouſand men; and where as 10000. pounds is demanded for all, he goe and pay a thouſand times as much for the ranſome of five as would have ranſomed them all; and his intent in paying ſuch a vaſt ſumme of money above what was demanded, was but the ranſome of five; and the intent of him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the money is to releaſe but five; Does the ſufficiency of this ranſome bind nim that receives it to releaſe all the reſt? no verily.</p>
            <p>So it is in this caſe, all were loſt in <hi>Adam,</hi> and became bondſlaves to ſinne and Satan; in ſuch ſpirituall bondage and Captivity, as no finite creature is able to pay the ranſome; Gods Law muſt be fulfilled, and his Iuſtice ſatisfied; None in Heaven or Earth could be found able to ranſome loſt mankind; The Father he gave his Son to purchaſe a Ranſome; the Son of God he paid a ranſome, and he paid a Ranſome ſo much greater then the offence, that he paid that for a few, that had been ſufficient, if it had been the will of God, to have Ranſomed not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a World, but a thouſand Worlds, and the Sons paying of it, and the Fathers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of it was but for a few; Does the ſufficiency of this Ranſome bind God to apply it to thoſe for whom he did not receive it, no, it cannot be; If a man that hath many debters will forgive one, is he bound to forgive all; God he payes the Ranſome himſelfe; and is not bound to pay it for all, nor to apply it to all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If Chriſt have not redeemed all, why doe you Miniſters offer Chriſt to all?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it is unknowne to us who they be that God hath rejected; they are knowne to God, but they are not knowne to us; And therefore in Chriſt's ſtead we beſeech poore ſoules to be reconciled, and offer Chriſt to all that will accept him upon Goſpel termes; but yet wee propound Chriſt upon ſuch conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as all have not, <hi>viz.</hi> To the humble ſoule, the hungry and thirſty ſoule, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Ioh</hi> 7.37. And the weary and heavie laden ſoule, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> Did God of old ordaine ſome to condemnation? This ſerves to condemne the generall Doctrine of the Prelates of late, who when they had come in the Pulpit, would ſay that we are all ſinners, but God in mercy hath given us a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ſo leave it; but they would ſeldome come to a ſearch of the conditions of their flocks; by laying open their miſery out of Chriſt, and ſhewing them the abſolute neceſſity of a Chriſt; and acquaint them with the many rocks and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the way to Heaven; and cry downe their ſinnes, their Swearing, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, uncleanneſſe, Sabbath prophanation, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaias</hi> commands, <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> 8.1. Crie aloud ſpare not, lift up thy voyce like a Trumpet, ſhew my people their tranſgreſſions, and the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> their ſinnes; Nay, did they not inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the Doctrine of Predeſtination to be taught in Churches, under a pretext of driving men to deſpaire; Seldome did we beare them reprove, rebuke, and exhort, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2 It they did reprove, and rebuke, it was the people of God, becauſe they did not joyne with them in their wicked Deſignes; And thus they would ſad the hearts of the righteous, and ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked; wheras, it is the duty of a Miniſter to put a difference betwixt the holy and prophane, at <hi>Ezek:</hi> 44.23. And they ſhall teach my people the difference between the holy and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162305:10"/>and cauſe them to diſcerne between the uncleane and the cleane; they ought to make ſuch a difference as the people may diſcerne between the good and the bad; to give to every one their portion, comfort to whom it belongs, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to whom it belongs; that they may ſhew themſelves approved of God, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that needeth not to be aſhamed, dividing the word of truth aright, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. But alas, whereas Miniſters of the word ſhould <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o burning and ſhining lights, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.35. How many might we looke upon in <hi>England</hi> that neither burne in Doctrine, nor ſhine in their converſation; but are ſcandalous in their lives; In ſtead of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving ſinne, they would ſweare and bee drunke, and uncleane; And who ſet worſe examples in many Pariſhes then their Miniſter; and when the Lordsday comes, if they did preach, it was to daube people with untempered morter, crying Peace, Peace, when they ſhould have cryed ſudgement and damnation; but oh! How ſad will their account be at the great day, where the bloud of their flocks ſhall be required at their hands.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Did God of old ordaine men to condemnation? This daſhes the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Pelagians,</hi> who hold univerſall grace, univerſall redemption, and univerſall pardon; A Doctrine condemned by all reformed Churches, yea, ſuch as once pretended a tender Conſcience; their Conſciences are now growne ſo ſeared, as they can joyne with the Prelates in this particuſer; They would have ſmooth things taught, and ſweet notions; but take heed yee doe not reprove ſinne, nor admoniſh to duty, for you ſhall ſoone heare of us then; and why ſo? Chriſt died for all. I find in Scripture that Chriſt dyed for his people; but I cannot find in Scripture that Chriſt died for the Reprobate; that he died for his people, is plaine, <hi>Math.</hi> 1.21. He ſhall ſave his people from their ſins, his people, not the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 5.25. Chriſt loved his Church and gave himſelfe for it, that he might ſanctifie it and cleanſe it; Marke, he gave himſelfe for his Church, and in the 10th. of <hi>Iohn</hi> he ſaith, he layes downe his life for his ſheep, but he doth not ſay he layd downe his life for them that are not his ſheep; ſo in <hi>Eſay</hi> 53. For the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of my people was he plagued; and divers other texts of Scripture I might alledge, which plainely proves that Chriſt dyed for his people, but they doe not prove that he dyed for the Reprobate; What a ſtrange Doctrine is it that ſome broach, that Chriſt dyed for the damned in hell, grounding it upon 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. They deny the Lord that bought them; which will appeare very abſurd, if wee conſider how they were bought. They were bought externally, but that they were bought with the bloud of Chriſt cannot appeare in the text. The Scripture ſhewes that God doth buy a people two wayes, either externally, when hee brings them into the bond of an outward Covenant, as he bought the <hi>Iewes, Hoſet</hi> 3.2. So I bought here to me for fifteene pieces of ſilver, and a homer and a halfe of Barley. And God is ſaid to buy his people with the bloud of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. Theſe, which denyed the Lord that bought them were externally bought; They looked upon themſelves as bought, and others looked upon them as bought, but if they had been bought with the bloud of Chriſt, it had been impoſſible that they ſhould periſh; for Chriſt ſaith in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10th I lay down my life for my ſheep, and I give them eternall life, and they ſhall never periſh; And <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.12. Of all that thou haſt given me, I have loſt none but the child of Periſition: From the word but the child of Perdition, the <hi>Pelagians</hi> object, that <hi>Iudas</hi> was given to Chriſt, as well as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162305:10"/>the reſt. I anſwer, that <hi>Iudas</hi> was externally given to Chriſt as an Apoſtle; but I deny that ever it was the intent of the Father in giving his Son to dye, or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Sonne in laying downe his life to ſhed his bloud for <hi>Iudas,</hi> or that ever <hi>Iudas</hi> was given to Chriſt as an elect veſſell; for if Chriſt had ſhed his bloud for him, and he had been given to Chriſt as an elect veſſell, hee could not have periſhed; for <hi>verſe</hi> the ſecond of this Chapter, We read, the Father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Sonne power over all fleſh, that hee ſhould give eternall life to as many as hee gave him; And ſeeng it was the Deſigne of the Father and the Sonne, to give eternall life to them that were given to Chriſt. Had <hi>Iudas</hi> been redeemed by the bloud of Chriſt, and given to Chriſt as an elect veſſell, hee could not have periſhed; Nay, had <hi>Iudas</hi> been given to Chriſt as an elect veſſell, Ieſus Chriſt would not have loſt him; for ſo ſaith the text, I have loſt none but the child of Perdition; ſo <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.37. All that the Father hath given mee ſhall come to mee, And he that cometh to mee I caſt not away. Had <hi>Iudas</hi> been given to Chriſt as an elect veſſell, Ieſus Chriſt would not have caſt him off; for all them that Chriſt did redeeme ſhall be ſaved, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 53 10, 11. When hee ſhall make his ſoule an offering for ſinne, hee ſhall ſee his ſeed, he ſhall prolong his dayes, and the will of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand, hee ſhall ſee the travaile of his ſoule and ſhall be ſatisfied; ſo <hi>Job,</hi> 3.24 Hee will mercy on him, and ſay, deliver him that hee goe not downe into the pit, for I have received a Ranſome for him; If the Father hath received a Ranſome, hee will moſt certainely deliver ſuch, that they goe not downe into the pit; So, that if Chriſt had ranſomed all, as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> affirme, then all muſt be ſaved, but it is plaine in Scripture, that but a few are ſaved; and as plaine, that Chriſt ranſomed onely the elect, and that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the elect ſhall bee ſaved by Chriſt, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. Whom hee predeſtinated, that is, them whom he predeſtinated to life, them hee called, and whom hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, he juſtifies, and whom he juſtifies, them he alſo glorifies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Is for examination; Did God of old ordaine men to condemnation; then wee ſhould every one of us examine, whether we be in an eſtate of ſalvation: When wee heare ſome ſhall periſh, me thinks every one ſhould put it to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether I am one of then. When Chriſt ſaid, one of you ſhall betray me, every one began to queſtion, is it I, ſo when you heare ſome ſhall periſh, mee thinks every one ſhould be ready to <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, is it I, oh! I pray God it may not be I. How ſhould this put you on, to give all diligence to make your calling and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But how ſhall I know I am none of thoſe that God did ordaine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whom God hath elected and whom he hath rejected wee know not, as I told you b<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e, neither is it neceſſary that wee ſhould know; but yet thou mayſt know for thy owne particu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, that God hath predeſtinated thee to life; Firſt, by thy effectual <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe that he predeſtinated to life them he called; I meane not a bare outward call, but an inward call by the word and Spirit: When God doth not onely by his word ſay to a poore ſoule as Chriſt did to <hi>Mathew,</hi> when he ſate at the receipt of the cuſion<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, but inables the ſoule to ariſe and follow him, as <hi>Matthew</hi> aroſe and followed Chriſt, <hi>Matthew</hi> 9.9.</p>
            <p>It is a calling the ſoule from ſinne, from amongſt the reſt of the world unto Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162305:11"/>Chriſt, and inables the ſoule to follow Chriſt, examine thy ſelfe, Hath the Lord thus effectually called thee, that thou haſt left all to follow Chriſt; this is a ſigne thou wert predeſtinated, for whom hee predeſtinateth, them he alſo calleth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</p>
            <p>Secondly, haſt thou true ſaving faith, juſtifying faith, whom he predeſtinated to life, hee works faith in them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. So many as were ordained to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life beleeved. When God hath a people to call home to himſelfe, he either brings them to the meanes, or the meanes to them; and thoſe that doe belong to the election of grace beleeve, and the reſt are hardned; Haſt thou this ſaving faith, not a fancied faith, a dead faith, an eaſie faith; but ſaving faith, ſuch a faith as was wrought in thee by the word and Spirit with power; ſuch a faith as was not in the power to give, nor in thy power to receive, untill God inabled thee by his Spirit; then thy faith doth evidence to thee that thou art ordained to life; for whom hee cals, he juſtifies, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.30. And wee are juſtified by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. Not that the eſſence of faith juſtifies; for it is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt juſtifies, but faith juſtifies inſtrumentally, in that it layes hold upon that which juſtifies the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whom hee predeſtinates to li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as hee calls them and juſtifies them, ſo he ſanctifies and glorifies them, this ſanctification is begun in this life; God prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinates his people unto holineſſe; He choſe us in Chriſt before the foundation of the world, that wee ſhould be holy, and without blame before him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.4. This ſanctification is begun here, and ſhall be perfect in glory; examine, haſt thou this evidence of thy election, thy ſanctification? Art thou holy? Is thy life holy? Doeſt thou walke exactly, as the grace of God which brings Salvation teacheth, to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live holily, righteouſly, and ſoberly in this preſent world, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. This is another evidence of thy election.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Uſe.</hi> Is Conſolation to all ſuch as finde upon examination, that they have good evidence of their election, all ſuch as God have let read their names in the the Booke of life, you may goe home and rejoyce, and take ſtrong conſolation, becauſe God hath predeſtinated you to life, and your names are written in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and if hee hath predeſtinated you to life, and writ your names in Heaven; Who ſhall be able to blot them out againe? None in Heaven or Earth ſhall ever be able to blot out thy name out of the Booke of life; therefore let us ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> What ſhall ſeperate us from the love of God? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. All that men and Devills can doe, cannot ſeparate thee from Gods love, nothing that ever hath been, is, or ſhall be that can ſeparate thee from Gods love. There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. God hath decreed thy ſalvation, and Gods decree ſhall ſtand, let men and Devils ſay what they will to the contrary, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. The Counſell of the Lord ſhall ſtand for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore. It is as poſſible for God to deny himſelfe, as it is poſſible for thee to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; for, We are kept ſaith the Apoſtle, by the power of God through faith to ſalvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. And therefore as our Saviour Chriſt ſaid to the ſeventie, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20. Rojoyce not that the Spirits are ſubdued unto you, but rather rejoyce that your names are written in Heaven. So ſay I, and more, rejoyce not onely that your names are written in Heaven; but rejoyce that your names are written in Heaven, and can never be blotted out againe.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:162305:11"/>
            <p> Secondly, as I would have you rejoyce, ſo I would have you alſo humble; Why did God predeſtinate thee to life? what, becauſe hee ſaw thee better then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or becauſe of unſeen m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rits or workes? no ſurely; before <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> had done good or evill ſaith the Lord, <hi>Iacob</hi> have I loved, <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated; They were two in one wombe, and God choſe the one, and refuſed the other, to ſhew to us, that it is of his free mercy and grace, according to his good pleaſure; I knew ſaith the Lord thou wouldſt tranſgreſſe from the wombe, <hi>Iſay</hi> 48.8. And I called thee a tranſgreſſour from the wombe; And <hi>Amos</hi> the 9.7. Were yee not as the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> unto mee, ſaith the Lord; So, May not the Lord ſay of thee, thou art a damned Creature, it was I that ſaved thee, thou wert a loſt Creature, it was I found thee; thou had'ſt deſtroyed thy ſelfe, it was I ſaid Thy help in is me; thou layeſt in thy bloud and filthineſſe, and no eye pitied thee; it was I ſpread my skirt over thee, and waſhed thee from thy filthineſſe, and entered into a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with thee, It was of his free grace to predeſtinate thee to life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be humble, and give him the glory of his free-grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as it is your duty to rejoyce, and to be humble, ſo alſo to be thankfull, that God ſhould looke upon you, and predeſtinate you to life: When hee paſſes by ſo many on the right hand, and the left, as the Scripture expreſſion is. There is but a remnant according to the election of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. And that I ſhould be one of them would the ſoule ſay, ſuch a vild and ſinfull wretched creature as I; Was there ever the like love? was there ever the like mercy? May not Heaven and Earth ſtand amazed at it? Oh! what ſhall I doe to be thankfull enough to this God? oh! you know your Intereſt is in Chriſt, ſtudie prayſes and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, not a verball thankfulneſſe but a reall thankfulneſſe, ſhew it by your obedience, by your holy converſation; by your walking ſutable to your place, as in 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 9. Yee are a choſen Generation, a Royall Prieſthood, a holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a peculiar people, that yee ſhould ſhew forth the vertues of him which hath called you out of darkneſſe unto his marvellous light; ſo ſhould Chriſtians walke according to their place; that God may be glorified by their holy converſation; God hath choſen the Saints to be holy, and called them to holineſſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, be yee holy, for I am holy, and therefore the Saints ſhould ſtudie holineſſe, and ſhew their thankfulneſſe in a holy obedience.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Uſe:</hi> If God hath of old ordained ſome to condemnation: then hence bee you exhorted, as you would be glad to know you are none of them, to give all diligence to make your calling and election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet:</hi> 1.10. Not but that it is ſure in reſpect of God, but the meaning is, to uſe all meanes to make it ſure to our ſoules and Conſciences.</p>
            <p>But it may bee you will ſay, why ſhould I uſe the meanes, if God have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed I ſhall be ſaved, I ſhall, if hee have decreed that I ſhall periſh, I ſhall, doe I what I can, and uſe what meanes I can.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, What haſt thou to doe to pry into Gods ſecret Counſell concerning thy election; though God hath decreed to paſſe by ſome, yet hee does not name thee for one; but have appointed the uſe of the meanes, and call upon thee to make thy election ſure; ſo that it is thy duty to uſe the meanes, and leave ſecres things to God; for God hath appointed how long every man ſhall live, and they cannot paſſe that time that God hath appointed them, <hi>Iob</hi> 14.5. He hath ſee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:162305:12"/>his bounds that hee can not paſſe; but withall as hee hath appointed how long everyone ſhould live; ſo he hath appointed the uſe of the meanes for the preſervation and maintenance of life to ſuch a time, as to dwell in houſes, weare cloathes, eat and drinke; will any man ſay, God hath appointed my time and I ſhall live that time whether I uſe the meanes or no; no ſurely, but will uſe the meanes God hath appointed; ſo God hath appointed the uſe of I meanes for the attaining the Knowledge of our election? Would wee make it ture then, we muſt uſe the meanes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> I might uſe many motives to put you upon the uſe of the meanes, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſpeake but of one or two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, conſider there is a poſſibility of making thy Calling and Election ſure; Why ſhould the Apoſtle exhort to it, if it were not poſſible, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your ſelves faith the Apoſtle, whether you bee in the Faith, prove your ſelves, know you not your owne ſelves Ieſus Chriſt is in you, except yee bee Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates. Why ſhould the Apoſtle exhort to try, prove, and examine our ſelves, if it were not poſſible to know that our Calling and Election is ſure.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider thou canſt have no comfort in the neglect of the uſe of the meanes but rather terrour; becauſe thy perſeveting in the neglect of the uſe of the meanes will rather evidence to thee, that thou art not Elected; for you ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. Thoſe he Predeſtinated hee called; that is thoſe that God predeſtinated to life, hee calls in his due time, and therefore wee muſt looke for a call or not looke to come into the Kingdome of Heaven; doth God let thee ſit ſtill in ſecuritie in thy carnall condition under the meanes, many a hard heart have been ſoftned and many a blind mind inlightned, many a unbeleeving ſoule have got faith in Chriſt in the uſe of meanes; and thou art a hard-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sinner ſtill, haſt a blind mind ſtill, lie in unbeliefe ſtill, lye frozen in the dregs of ſecuritie. I tell thee if thou goeſt on and die in this condition, thou muſt bee ſure to periſh, for thy perſevering in this eſtate is a ſigne that God did not decree to ſave thee. It will appeare if thou compare <hi>Acts</hi> 15.38. with <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.26. in <hi>Acts.</hi> 13.58. So many as were ordained to Eternall life belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thus, That whom God did Predeſtinate to eternall life, hee did predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to faith to beleeve in Chriſt And therefore in time the Lord either ſends the meanes to them or them to the meanes, and calls them and workes Faith in them; and on the contrary, when the Word proves a hardening, a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning letter to the hearers, when it is not a word of Faith to them: It is a ſigne that God did not Predeſtinate them to life; for in the other text of Scripture, <hi>John</hi> 10.16. Yee beleeve not ſaith Chriſt, becauſe yee are not of my Sheepe; this is the Reaſon they were none of Chriſts ſheepe, and therefore could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve. And therefore take heed of neglecting the uſe of the meanes, and roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thy ſelfe aſleepe with this, If God have decreed I ſhall be ſaved I ſhall; I tell you many have ſtumbled and fallen upon his Rocke, and ſo mayeſt thou if the Lord bee not mercifull to thee, Mee thinkes this ſhould make ſuch trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as are in the ſtate of unbeleefe and impenitencie, and hard-heartedneſſe under the meanes; how ſhouldeſt thou tremble ever when thou ſeeſt any of thy Companions brought in to Ieſus Chriſt, ſuch a fellow Drunkard, ſuch a fellow Sweater, ſuch a vild wretch the Lord brought home; and I am yet lefe in ſinne,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:162305:12"/>I am yet uncalled, unjuſtified, unſanctified, and yet I muſt bee called or hee damned; for tall thoſe that God predeſtinates to life, hee calls them in his due time; I mee thinks, I feare God hath not predeſtinated mee to life, that hee lets mee alone in ſinne, oh Brethren! that you would conſider of theſe things; thou that art a husband, and looke upon thy wife that is godly, and thou act ungodly ſtill; With what ſad thoughts may'ſt thou thinke of this; Oh! God hath called my wife, and manifeſted his love to her, ſhee hath left her former ſinnes, and ſhe walks cloſe with God; but I am uncalled ſtill, and I goe on in the wayes of ſinne ſtill; Oh! had God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended good to mee, ſurely he would call mee, and give mee a new heart; and with the like ſad <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ghts may ungodly Wives looke upon their godly Husbands; And ungodly companions, who it may be have many a time ſcoffed and jeered at others of their companions, becauſe they have left their former ſinnes, and walke more cloſe with God, out oh! they might looke upon them with weeping eyes, it they would conſider this, that thoſe that God predeſtinates to life, them hee calls, and them he juſtifies, them hee gives faith too, As many as were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to eternall life beleeved; and yet he hath to this day let them alone in their ſinnes to goe on after the hardneſſe of their hearts: as if the Lord ſhould ſay to them as to <hi>Ephraim, Hoſea</hi> 4.17. He is joyned to Idols, let him alone, let them goe on in their ſinnes, and periſh in their ſinnes, if they will die ungodly men and women. Conſider of this; They could not but mourne and lament their conditions; and therefore let this Doctrine be rather an incouragement, to put you on, to give all diligence to make your calling and election ſure; then a ground of preſumption or deſpaire.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
